Guide to the Savannah Port Papers, 1754-1920 RL.10081
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Savannah Port papers
1754-1920
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Port of Savannah (Ga.)
RL.10081
20 Linear Feet 5,594 items
This collection contains the official papers of the Port of Savannah, Georgia, in the Governmental Coastal District of Savannah. They are papers of ship clearance, cargo lists, Treasury Department letters and similar papers which deal with the customs operations at the port from 1820 to 1920. Although the papers mainly consist of cargo manifests, there are also letters, legal documents, literary pieces, and other miscellaneous items. Several of the items deal with slavery in Savannah and there are occasional mentions of piracy, smuggling, and general misdeeds among the seamen.
Collection Overview
The official papers of the port of Savannah cover a myriad of topics, but are primarily comprised of documents pertaining to customs, import and export trade, and shipping. The general papers include ship clearance papers, cargo lists, crew lists, crew bonds, customs papers, salary receipts for port officials, and warehouse papers. The general correspondence includes letters from everyday port transactions and affairs, United States Treasury Department letters, and letters from the British consulate. There are papers concerning construction and maintenance of lighthouses, particularly the Tybee Island Lighthouse. These papers also include a number of legal documents, mostly bills of sale and deeds for land, livestock, sea vessels, and slaves. Other items include lists of seamen admitted to the Savannah poor house and hospital in the 1820s and 1830s, miscellaneous literary documents, and papers of the Savannah Port Society, a charitable organization to aid indigent seamen. Included also is a letter book, 1817-1826, of A. S. Bullock, collector of the port of Savannah, giving many references to economic conditions; a volume listing the persons who entered the port of Savannah, 1817-1818; and volumes containing lists of returns of goods on a number of ships, and inspectors' returns, 1830-1840. Items are arranged chronologically whenever possible.
Alternate Form Available
Microfilm available.
Provenance
The Savannah Port Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1939 and 1956.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Lighthouses -- Georgia -- Savannah.; Savannah (Ga.) -- Commerce; Merchant mariners -- Missions and charities -- Georgia.; Customs administration -- Georgia -- Savannah.; Georgia -- Commerce.; Savannah (Ga.) -- Economic conditions.; Shipping -- Georgia -- Savannah.; Port of Savannah (Ga.)
- Savannah Port Papers
  - General Port Papers, 1754-1918
    Scope and Contents
    This series consists of the official papers of the Port of Savannah, Georgia. It mainly contains ship clearance papers, cargo lists, and other documents that were a part of customs operations at the time. The documents date from 1754 to 1918, but the bulk of the items are from the early to mid-1800s.The manifests detail cargo entering and leaving the port. The Returns of Seamen papers list the crews shipping on the vessels. There are also import customs papers, which detail the customs due on each item. The Warehouse Withdrawal papers are permits to withdraw stored items from warhouses. Importers were allowed to place liquors and otherarticles in bonded warehouses until sold and then pay the duty as they withdrew them from the houses. Also included are lists of ship stores. The crew bonds are bonds binding vessel masters to return to port with the same crews with which they ship out, unless some be discharged in foreign ports with permission of the U.S. Consul in that port. There are also salary receipts of the various United States officials necessary to administer the work of the District of Savannah, and receipts and disbursement accounts of various sorts for the Port of Savannah, District of Savannah.
    Of these papers, by far the largest part are manifests, either of a part of the cargo or of the whole cargo. The next largest groups include Returns of Seamen and Import Custom papers, and the other items are in much smaller proportions.
    Several interesting observations arise from a study of this collection. One of these concerns the chief items of export from Savannah during the years of this set. The one item which composed the largest part of the export trade was up-land, or short-staple colton. Most of this went to Liverpool, and the return cargoes consisted largely of iron, steel, and manufactured goods.There was some Sea Island Cotton to export, but not nearly so much of it as of the upland. Two or three manifests, one in 1851, show that often ships came down from Boston and New England with cargoes of ice. The 1851 manifest shows a cargo of 124 tons of ice from Boston to Savannah. Most of the other cargoes from New England consisted mainly of food.Two other items occur often in the export manifests from Savannah. One is rice. This commodity formed a part of many cargoes, and quite a few times was the whole cargo. The other item was lumber, notably pine, in the form of boards and shingles. Much of this went to Liverpool, and much of it to Barbados, Havana, and other island ports, but, interestingly enough, a considerable quantity was sent North to New England ports. Much wine was imported from Madeira and then exported again to European ports, notably Liverpool. The main European ports receiving Savannah exports were Liverpool and Havre.
    Items are arranged chronologically. There are several boxes of oversized documents also arranged chronologically.
    - General Papers, 1754-1809 (Box 1)
    - General Papers, 1800-1822 (Box 26)
      Oversize.
    - General Papers, 1810-1811; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - General Papers, 1812-1815; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - General Papers, 1816-1819; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - General Papers, 1820 Jan-June; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - General Papers, 1820 July-1822; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - General Papers, 1823-1827 (Box 26)
    - General Papers, 1823-1826; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - General Papers, 1827 (Box 2)
    - General Papers, 1828 (Box 26)
    - General Papers, 1828 (Box 2)
    - General Papers, 1829 Jan-Mar (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1829 Apr-May (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1829 June-Aug (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1829 Sept-Oct (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1829 Jan-Mar (Box 2)
    - General Papers, 1829 Apr-May (Box 3)
    - General Papers, 1829 June-Aug (Box 3)
    - General Papers, 1829 Sept-Oct (Box 3)
    - General Papers, 1829 Nov-Dec (Box 3)
    - General Papers, 1830 Jan-Mar (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1830 Apr-July (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1830 Aug-Nov (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1830 Dec-Mar (Box 25)
    - General Papers, 1830 Jan-Mar (Box 3)
    - General Papers, 1830 Apr-July (Box 3)
    - General Papers, 1830 Aug-Nov (Box 3)
    - General Papers, 1830 Dec-1831 Mar (Box 4)
    - General Papers, 1831 Apr-Dec (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1831 Apr-Dec (Box 4)
    - General Papers, 1832 (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1832 Jan-May (Box 4)
    - General Papers, 1832 June-Nov. (Box 4)
    - General Papers, 1832 Dec (Box 4)
    - General Papers, 1833 (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1833 Jan-June; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - General Papers, 1833 July-Dec (Box 5)
    - General Papers, 1834 (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1834 Jan (Box 5)
    - General Papers, 1834 Feb-Mar; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - General Papers, 1834 Apr 1-15 (Box 6)
    - General Papers, 1834 Apr 16-22 (Box 6)
    - General Papers, 1834 Apr 23-30 (Box 6)
    - General Papers, 1834 May; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - General Papers, 1834 June (Box 6)
    - General Papers, 1834 July (Box 7)
    - General Papers, 1834 Aug-Dec; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - General Papers, 1835 (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1835 Jan-May (Box 7)
    - General Papers, 1835 June-Nov (Box 7)
      Includes three documents from November and December of 1835 pertaining to the brig Ann Maria and its cargo. Thirty-three slaves are listed alongside sea stores and cargo. The documents are from the Port of Alexandria and the Port of Savannah.
    - General Papers, 1835 Dec; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - General Papers, 1836-1837 (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1836 Jan-Feb (Box 8)
    - General Papers, 1836 Mar-Nov; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - General Papers, 1836 Dec (Box 8)
    - General Papers, 1837; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - General Papers, 1838-1842 (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1838 Jan-Feb (Box 9)
    - General Papers, 1838 Mar (Box 9)
    - General Papers, 1838 Apr (Box 9)
    - General Papers, 1838 May-June (Box 10)
    - General Papers, 1838 Oct-Dec (Box 10)
    - General Papers, 1839 Jan-July (Box 10)
    - General Papers, 1839 Aug-Dec (Box 10)
    - General Papers, 1840 Jan-Mar (Box 11)
    - General Papers, 1840 April; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - General Papers, 1840 May-Nov (Box 11)
    - General Papers, 1841 (Box 11)
    - General Papers, 1842 (Box 12)
    - General Papers, 1843 (Box 12)
    - General Papers, 1843-1846 (Box 24)
    - General Papers, 1844 Jan-June (Box 12)
    - General Papers, 1844 July-Dec (Box 12)
    - General Papers, 1845-1846 (Box 13)
    - General Papers, 1847 Jan (Box 13)
    - General Papers, 1847 Feb-Dec (Box 13)
    - General Papers, 1847-1849 (Box 23)
    - General Papers, 1848-1849 (Box 13)
    - General Papers, 1850 (Box 23)
    - General Papers, 1850 Jan-July; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - General Papers, 1850 Aug-Dec (Box 13)
    - General Papers, 1851 (Box 23)
    - General Papers, 1851 Jan-Apr (Box 14)
    - General Papers, 1851 May-Dec (Box 14)
    - General Papers, 1852-1853 (Box 23)
    - General Papers, 1852-1853 Mar (Box 14)
    - General Papers, 1853 Apr-June (Box 14)
    - General Papers, 1853 July-Dec (Box 14)
    - General Papers, 1854 (Box 23)
    - General Papers, 1854 Jan (Box 14)
    - General Papers, 1854 Feb-Dec (Box 15)
    - General Papers, 1855 (Box 23)
    - General Papers, 1855 Jan-Mar (Box 15)
    - General Papers, 1855 Apr (Box 15)
    - General Papers, 1855 May (Box 15)
    - General Papers, 1855 June-Sept (Box 15)
    - General Papers, 1855 Oct-Dec (Box 15)
    - General Papers, 1856 (Box 22)
    - General Papers, 1856 Jan-Feb (Box 15)
    - General Papers, 1856 Feb-Mar (Box 16)
    - General Papers, 1856 Apr-June (Box 16)
    - General Papers, 1856 July-Sept (Box 16)
    - General Papers, 1856 Oct-Dec (Box 16)
    - General Papers, 1857 (Box 22)
    - General Papers, 1857 (Box 16)
    - General Papers, 1858 (Box 22)
    - General Papers, 1858 Jan (Box 16)
    - General Papers, 1858 Feb-May (Box 16)
    - General Papers, 1858 July-Dec (Box 17)
    - General Papers, 1859; 2 folders (Box 22)
    - General Papers, 1859 Jan-June (Box 17)
    - General Papers, 1859 July-Sept (Box 17)
    - General Papers, 1859 Oct (Box 17)
    - General Papers, 1859 Nov (Box 17)
    - General Papers, 1859 Dec (Box 17)
    - General Papers, 1859
    - General Papers, 1860 (Box 21)
    - General Papers, 1860 Jan (Box 18)
    - General Papers, 1860 Feb (Box 18)
    - General Papers, 1860 Mar-Aug (Box 18)
    - General Papers, 1860 Sept-Oct (Box 18)
    - General Papers, 1860 Nov-Dec (Box 18)
    - General Papers, 1861 (Box 21)
    - General Papers, 1861 Jan-Feb (Box 18)
    - General Papers, 1861 Mar 5-15 (Box 18)
    - General Papers, 1861 Mar 16-Dec (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1863-1865 (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1866 (Box 21)
    - General Papers, 1866 Jan-Sept (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1866 Oct-Dec (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1867-1918 (Box 21)
    - General Papers, 1867 (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1868 (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1869 Jan-Mar (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1869 Apr-Dec (Box 19)
    - General Papers, 1870-1900 (Box 20)
    - General Papers, 1901-1918 (Box 20)
    - General Papers, undated; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Legal Documents
    - Bills of Sale - Livestock, 1837-1842 (Box 27)
    - Bills of Sale - Slaves, 1822-1831; 2 folders (Box 27, Box 26)
    - Bills of Sale - Land, 1814-1859; 2 folders (Box 27, Box 26)
    - Bills of Sale - Sea Vessels, 1829-1858 (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous Legal Documents, 1824-1865 (Box 27)
      Various fragments, copies of ordinances and other items that are legal in nature.
  - General Correspondence, 1820-1883, undated; 3 folders
    The correspondence contains various letters to and from the British Consulate in the Port of Savannah, as well as correspondence regarding the day-to-day operations of the port. Also among the letters are many requests for information on British citizens presumed dead and thought to have settled in Savannah. These letters are generally seeking for portions of inheritances. The letters to the British consulate often request financial aid or travel back to Britain. Among these letters of the British consulate is a note from Jefferson Davis, allowing a British subject to travel freely without threat of conscription (January 2, 1865).
    Particular letters of interest include the following:
    1) A letter dated December 12, 1819 that includes details on the prosecution of certain prisoners who were part of the crew of the piratical ship Louisa and were charged with piracy and murder.
    2) A letter dated March 10, 1820 with a complaint about port fees.
    3) A letter dated October 27, 1843 detailing a complaint against the master of a particular ship and his theft of broadcloths and linens. This was not his first act of impropriety and the author of the letter urges the port to recognize him as a "shameless smuggler."
    4) A letter dated February 2, 1853 urging its recipient that "by sending the negroes to Charleston they would bring a higher price."
  - Savannah Port Society Papers, 1901-1920, undated; 2 folders (Box 20)
    The papers of the Savannah Port Society, a charitable organization to aid indigent seamen.
  - Volumes
    - A.S. Bullock Letterbook, 1817-1826 (Box 28)
      Letterbook of A. S. Bullock, collector of the port of Savannah at least from 1817 to 1822, containing copies of routine letters relative to the port of Savannah. The routine letters, however, contain considerable information. Among them are accounts of pirate ships, smuggling of slaves, escape of slaves in ships, burning of the customs house at Savannah, Tybee Light House and its equipment, and other related matters. Frequently Bullock's letters request information on legal matters from the district attorney. A few letters at the end of the volume were written by N.A. Olmstead, Deputy collector.
    - Inspectors Returns, 1830-1840 (Box 29)
    - Cargo Returns Ledger, 1817-1824 (Box 29)
    - Protection, 1817-1818 (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous Documents
    - Literary Documents, 1828-1859, undated (Box 27)
      Contains handwritten poetry, the Song of the Charleston Light Dragoons at their 24th Anniversary Supper, and other miscellaneous literary items.
    - Account of Certificates Issued for Distilled Spirits, Wines, and Teas, 1827 (Box 27)
      Unbound.
    - Poor House Hospital Documents (Box 27)
      Documents pertaining to the medical care of seamen.
    - Tybee Lighthouse Papers (Box 27, Oversize-folder 1)
      Contracts, letters, bills, receipts, proposals, etc., that deal with the upkeep of the Tybee Lighthouse.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27)
      Fragments and unidentified items.